<!-- #################################################################### -->
<!-- ##                                                                ## -->
<!-- ##  about.xml          RCWA documentation            Stefan Kohl  ## -->
<!-- ##                                                                ## -->
<!-- ##  $Id$         ## -->
<!-- ##                                                                ## -->
<!-- #################################################################### -->

<Chapter Label="ch:AboutRCWA"><Heading>About the RCWA Package</Heading>

<!-- #################################################################### -->

<Section Label="sec:motivation">
<Heading>Motivation</Heading>

<Index Key="Collatz conjecture">Collatz conjecture</Index>
<Index Key="Collatz conjecture">Collatz mapping</Index>
The development of this package has originally been inspired by the famous
<M>3n+1</M>-Conjecture, which asserts that iterated application of the
<E>Collatz mapping</E>
<Alt Only="LaTeX">
  <Display>
  <![CDATA[
    T: \ \ \Z \longrightarrow \Z, \ \ \ \
    n \ \longmapsto \
    \begin{cases}
      \frac{n}{2}    & \text{if} \ \ n \ \ \text{is even}, \\
      \frac{3n+1}{2} & \text{if} \ \ n \ \ \text{is odd}
    \end{cases}
  ]]>
  </Display>
</Alt>
<Alt Only="Text,HTML"><Verb><![CDATA[
                                       /
                                      | n/2 if n even,
               T:  Z -> Z,   n  |->  <
                                      | (3n+1)/2 if n odd
                                       \
]]></Verb></Alt>
to any given positive integer eventually yields&nbsp;1
(cp.&nbsp;<Cite Key="Lagarias06"/>). <P/>

So far, no attempts have been made to investigate the structure of groups
whose elements are permutations which are <Q>similar to the Collatz
mapping</Q>, i.e. <E>residue-class-wise affine</E>. <P/>

After having investigated these groups for a couple of years,
the author feels that this is a gap which is worth to be filled.

</Section>

<!-- #################################################################### -->

<Section Label="sec:GroupsWhichEmbed">
<Heading>Groups which can be dealt with</Heading>

In principle this package permits to construct and investigate all groups
which have faithful representations as residue-class-wise affine groups.
A couple of types of such groups are listed in the abstract.
From the list given there, one can already conclude that there are
finitely generated residue-class-wise affine groups which do not have
finite presentations, and such with unsolvable membership problem.
However the list is by far not exhaustive. <P/>

The group which is generated by all <E>class transpositions</E>
-- these are involutions which interchange two disjoint residue classes,
see <Ref Func="ClassTransposition" Label="r1, m1, r2, m2"/> -- is a simple
group which has subgroups of all types listed in the abstract.
It is countable, but it has an uncountable series of simple subgroups
which is parametrized by the sets of odd primes. <P/>

Proofs of most of the results mentioned here and in the abstract have
not yet appeared in print. However they can be found in the
preprint&nbsp;<Cite Key="Kohl06b"/>, which is available on the author's
homepage. Descriptions of many of the algorithms and methods which are
implemented in this package can be found in&nbsp;<Cite Key="Kohl07a"/>.

</Section>

<Alt Only="LaTeX">\pagebreak[4]</Alt>

<!-- #################################################################### -->

<Section Label="sec:Purpose">
<Heading>Purpose of this package</Heading>

So far, compared to classes of groups like for example finite groups,
matrix groups, finitely presented groups or polycyclic groups, not very much
is known about residue-class-wise affine groups. This package is intended
to serve as a tool for obtaining a better understanding of their rich and
interesting group theoretical and combinatorial structure.

</Section>

<!-- #################################################################### -->

<Section Label="sec:Scope">
<Heading>Scope of this package</Heading>

This package can be applied in various ways to various different problems,
and it is just not possible to say what can be found out with its help
about which groups. The best way to get an idea about this is likely to
experiment with the examples discussed in this manual and included in the
file <File>pkg/rcwa/examples/examples.g</File>. <P/>

Of course this package often does not provide an out-of-the-box solution
for a given problem. Quite often it is possible to find an answer for
a given question by using an interactive trial-and-error approach. <P/>

With substancial help of this package, the author has found the results
mentioned in Section&nbsp;<Ref Label="sec:GroupsWhichEmbed"/>.
Interactive sessions with this package have also lead to the development
of most of the algorithms which are now implemented in it. Just to mention
one example, developing the factorization method for residue-class-wise
affine permutations (see&nbsp;<Ref Attr="FactorizationIntoCSCRCT"
Label="g"/>) solely by means of theory would likely have been very hard.

</Section>

<!-- #################################################################### -->

</Chapter>

<!-- #################################################################### -->
