<!-- #################################################################### -->
<!-- ##                                                                ## -->
<!-- ##  abstract.xml         RCWA documentation          Stefan Kohl  ## -->
<!-- ##                                                                ## -->
<!-- ##  $Id$     ## -->
<!-- ##                                                                ## -->
<!-- #################################################################### -->

<Abstract>

&RCWA; is a package for &GAP; 4 which provides methods for investigating
<E>R</E>esidue <E>C</E>lass-<E>W</E>ise <E>A</E>ffine groups by means of
computation.

Residue class-wise affine groups are countable permutation groups acting
on the integers, whose elements are bijective residue class-wise affine
mappings. <P/>

A mapping <M>f: \Z \rightarrow \Z</M> is called <E>residue class-wise
affine</E> provided that there is a positive integer <M>m</M> such that the
restrictions of <M>f</M> to the residue classes (mod&nbsp;<M>m</M>) are all
affine. This means that for any residue class <M>r(m) \in \Z/m\Z</M> there
are coefficients <M>a_{r(m)}, b_{r(m)}, c_{r(m)} \in \Z</M> such that
the restriction of the mapping&nbsp;<M>f</M> to the set
<M>r(m) = \{{r + km | k \in \Z\}}</M> is given&nbsp;by
<Alt Only = "LaTeX">
  <Display>
    f|_{r(m)}: \ \ r(m) \rightarrow \Z, \ \ \
    n \ \mapsto \ \frac{a_{r(m)} \cdot n + b_{r(m)}}{c_{r(m)}}.
  </Display>
</Alt>
<Alt Only = "Text,HTML"><Verb>
                                        a_r(m) * n + b_r(m)
           f|_r(m):  r(m) -> Z,  n |->  -------------------.
                                              c_r(m)
</Verb></Alt>
<Q>Many</Q> residue class-wise affine groups act multiply transitively
on&nbsp;<M>\Z</M> or on subsets thereof. The class of groups which can
faithfully be represented as residue class-wise affine groups is closed
under forming wreath products with finite groups and with the infinite
cyclic group <M>(\Z,+)</M>. It includes free groups of any rank, all free
products of finite groups and certain divisible torsion groups. It also
contains finitely generated groups with unsolvable membership problem. The
group which is generated by all <E>class transpositions</E> -- these are
involutions which interchange two disjoint residue classes -- is a simple
group which has subgroups of all mentioned types and whose class of
isomorphism types of subgroups is closed under the above operations. <P/>

Despite of what has been said in the preceding paragraph, only comparatively
basic facts about the structure of residue class-wise affine groups are known
so far. This package is intended to serve as a tool for obtaining a better
understanding of their rich and interesting group theoretical and
combinatorial structure. <P/>

Residue class-wise affine groups can be generalized in a natural way to
euclidean rings other than the ring of integers. While this package
undoubtedly provides most functionality for residue class-wise affine groups
over the integers, at least rudimentarily it also covers the cases that the
underlying ring is a semilocalization of&nbsp;<M>\Z</M> or a polynomial ring
in one variable over a finite field. <P/>

The original motivation for investigating residue class-wise affine groups
comes from the famous <M>3n+1</M> Conjecture, which is an assertion about
a surjective, but not injective residue class-wise affine mapping. <P/>

Residue class-wise affine groups are introduced in the author's thesis
<E>Restklassenweise affine Gruppen</E>. This thesis is published at
<URL>http://deposit.ddb.de/cgi-bin/dokserv?idn=977164071</URL>
(Archivserver Deutsche Bibliothek).
A copy of this thesis and an english translation thereof are distributed
with this package (see <F>thesis/thesis.pdf</F> resp.
<F>thesis/thesis&uscore;e.pdf</F>).

</Abstract>

<!-- #################################################################### -->
