<!-- #################################################################### -->
<!-- ##                                                                ## -->
<!-- ##  intro.xml          RCWA documentation            Stefan Kohl  ## -->
<!-- ##                                                                ## -->
<!-- ##  $Id$        ## -->
<!-- ##                                                                ## -->
<!-- #################################################################### -->

<Chapter Label="ch:Introduction"><Heading>Introduction</Heading>

<!-- #################################################################### -->

Having already defined rcwa mappings and rcwa groups in the Preface, we will
give a couple of basic definitions followed by a list of some elementary
properties of the defined objects, several examples, a very brief statement
of a few results and finally a few open questions in this chapter. <P/>

For everything not included in this manual (most theorems and lemmata,
all proofs, ...) the reader is referred to the author's thesis
<Cite Key="Kohl04" />. <P/>

We assume that on our underlying ring <M>R</M> we have defined a function
which maps each element to some <E>standard associate</E>. For the rings
treated in this package we have chosen the following:
<List>

  <Mark><M>\mathbb{Z}</M></Mark>
  <Item>
    The standard associate is the absolute value.
  </Item>

  <Mark><M>\mathbb{Z}_{(\pi)}</M></Mark>
  <Item>
    The standard associate of <M>n</M> is the largest product of
    non-invertible primes dividing <M>n</M>.
  </Item>

  <Mark>GF(<M>q</M>)[<M>x</M>]</Mark>
  <Item>
    We get our standard associate by dividing by the leading coefficient.
  </Item>

</List>

Whenever we write <Q>the lcm ...</Q> we always mean its standard associate.
We proceed with the definitions concerning rcwa mappings.

<Index Key="rcwa mapping" Subkey="modulus"></Index>
<Index Key="rcwa mapping" Subkey="multiplier"></Index>
<Index Key="rcwa mapping" Subkey="divisor"></Index>
<Index Key="rcwa mapping" Subkey="integral"></Index>
<Index Key="rcwa mapping" Subkey="prime set"></Index>
<Index Key="rcwa mapping" Subkey="tame"></Index>
<Index Key="rcwa mapping" Subkey="wild"></Index>

<List>

  <Mark>Modulus</Mark>
  <Item>
    The <E>Modulus</E> of an rcwa mapping <M>f</M> is the standard associate
    of a multiplicatively smallest ring element <M>m</M> such that the
    restriction of <M>f</M> to any residue class (mod <M>m</M>) is affine.
    <M>\rightarrow</M> <Ref Oper ="Modulus"
                            Label="Modulus of an rcwa mapping"/>.
  </Item>

  <Mark>Multiplier</Mark>
  <Item>
    In the notation we used in the definition of an rcwa mapping in the
    Preface (<Ref Label="ch:preface"/>), the <E>multiplier</E> is the
    lcm of the coefficients <M>a_{r(m)}</M> in the numerators.
    <M>\rightarrow</M> <Ref Attr ="Multiplier"
                            Label="Multiplier of an rcwa mapping"/>.
  </Item>

  <Mark>Divisor</Mark>
  <Item>
    In the notation we used in the definition of an rcwa mapping in the
    Preface (<Ref Label="ch:preface"/>), the <E>divisor</E> is the lcm
    of the coefficients <M>c_{r(m)}</M> in the denominators.
    <M>\rightarrow</M> <Ref Attr ="Divisor"
                            Label="Divisor of an rcwa mapping"/>.
  </Item>

  <Mark>integral</Mark>
  <Item>
    An rcwa mapping is called <E>integral</E> if its divisor equals 1,
    thus <Q>if no proper divisions occur</Q>.
    Be careful not to confuse this with the term <E>integral rcwa mapping</E>
    for rcwa mappings of the integers; normally it should be rather clear
    what is meant.
    <M>\rightarrow</M> <Ref Prop="IsIntegral" Label="Integral mapping"/>.
  </Item>

  <Mark>Prime Set</Mark>
  <Item>
    The set of prime divisors of the product of the modulus, the multiplier
    and the divisor of an rcwa mapping.
    <M>\rightarrow</M> <Ref Oper ="PrimeSet"
                            Label="Prime set of an rcwa mapping"/>.
  </Item>

  <Mark>tame</Mark>
  <Item>
    An rcwa mapping is called <E>tame</E> if the cyclic group it generates
    is tame (definition: see below). Tameness is a class invariant (this
    means that all conjugates of tame mappings are also tame).
    <M>\rightarrow</M> <Ref Prop="IsTame" Label="Tame rcwa mapping"/>.
  </Item>

  <Mark>wild</Mark>
  <Item>
    An rcwa mapping is called <E>wild</E> if it is not tame.
  </Item>

  <Mark>determinant</Mark>
  <Item>
    We define the <E>determinant</E> of an affine mapping
    <M>n \mapsto (an+b)/c</M> whose source is a residue class
    <M>r(m)</M> by <M>b/am</M>, and extend this definition additively
    to determinants of rcwa mappings and those restrictions to
    unions of residue classes.
    Then, using the notation from the definition of an rcwa mapping in the
    Preface (<Ref Label="ch:preface"/>), the <E>determinant</E> of an rcwa
    mapping is given by
    <Alt Not="LaTeX">
      (see LaTeX version of the manual).
    </Alt> 
    <Alt Only="LaTeX">
      <Display>
        \frac{1}{m}
        \left( \sum_{r(m) \in R/mR} \frac{b_{r(m)}}{a_{r(m)}} \right).
      </Display>
    </Alt>
    <M>\rightarrow</M> <Ref Meth="Determinant"/>.
  </Item>

</List>

Now the definitions concerning rcwa groups.

<Index Key="rcwa group" Subkey="modulus"></Index>
<Index Key="rcwa group" Subkey="tame"></Index>
<Index Key="rcwa group" Subkey="wild"></Index>
<Index Key="rcwa representation">rcwa representation</Index>
<Index Key="rcwa group" Subkey="integral"></Index>
<Index Key="rcwa group" Subkey="prime set"></Index>

<List>

  <Mark>Modulus</Mark>
  <Item>
    The <E>Modulus</E> of an rcwa group is the lcm of the moduli of its
    elements in case such an lcm exists and 0 otherwise.
    <M>\rightarrow</M> <Ref Oper ="Modulus"
                            Label="Modulus of an rcwa group"/>.
  </Item>

  <Mark>tame</Mark>
  <Item>
    An rcwa group is called <E>tame</E> if its modulus is not equal to 0.
    <M>\rightarrow</M> <Ref Prop="IsTame" Label="Tame rcwa group"/>.
  </Item>

  <Mark>wild</Mark>
  <Item>
    An rcwa group is called <E>wild</E> if it is not tame.
  </Item>

  <Mark>Rcwa Representation</Mark>
  <Item>
    An homomorphism from some group into the group RCWA(<M>R</M>)
    of all bijective rcwa mappings of the ring <M>R</M>.
  </Item>

  <Mark>integral</Mark>
  <Item>
    An rcwa group is called <E>integral</E> if all of its elements are.
    See also the warning given in the description of the corresponding
    property of rcwa mappings.
    <M>\rightarrow</M> <Ref Prop="IsIntegral" Label="Integral group"/>.
  </Item>

  <Mark>Prime Set</Mark>
  <Item>
    The <E>prime set</E> of an rcwa group is the union of the prime
    sets of its elements.
  </Item>

</List>

Listing a few relations between the terms defined so far should not be
left out in this context:

<List>

  <Mark>-</Mark>
  <Item>
    The divisor of an rcwa mapping divides its modulus.
    The modulus, multiplier resp. divisor of a product of rcwa mappings
    divides the product of the moduli, multipliers resp. divisors of the
    factors, and the prime set of a product of rcwa mappings is a subset
    of the union of the prime sets of the factors.
  </Item>

  <Mark>-</Mark>
  <Item>
    Inverting a bijective rcwa mapping interchanges multiplier and divisor.
    The product of the modulus and the multiplier of a bijective rcwa mapping
    is a multiple of the modulus of its inverse, which in turn is a multiple
    of the multiplier of the mapping we started with. The multiplier of an
    integral bijective rcwa mapping equals 1. Inversion leaves the prime
    set invariant.
  </Item>

</List>

<Alt Not="LaTeX">
  You are reading the HTML- or plaintext version of the &RCWA; manual --
  due to the typesetting limitations imposed by these file formats, we omit
  the examples paragraph and refer interested readers to the PDF- or
  Postscript version.
</Alt>

<Alt Only="LaTeX">

  How do rcwa mappings look like? --
  For purposes of illustrating the above definitions we list a number of
  examples. <P/>

  We have already mentioned the Collatz mapping, which is usually given
  in the following slightly more adequate form:
  <Display>
    <![CDATA[
    T: \ \mathbb{Z} \longrightarrow \mathbb{Z}, \ \ n \ \longmapsto \
    \begin{cases}
      \frac{n}{2}    & \text{if} \ n \ \text{is even}, \\
      \frac{3n+1}{2} & \text{otherwise}.
    \end{cases}
    ]]>
  </Display>
  The modulus of this mapping is 2, its multiplier is 3 and its divisor is 2,
  thus its prime set is <M>\{2,3\}</M>. The mapping <M>T</M> is surjective
  but not injective, as it bijectively maps the residue class 0(2) onto
  <M>\mathbb{Z}</M> and the residue class 1(2) onto 2(3). <P/>

  A bijective rcwa mapping of the integers, thus an element of
  RCWA(<M>\mathbb{Z}</M>), which has already been investigated by several
  people before is given by
  <Display>
    <![CDATA[
    a: \ \mathbb{Z} \longrightarrow \mathbb{Z}, \ \ n \ \longmapsto \
    \begin{cases}
      \frac{3n}{2}      & \text{if} \ n \equiv 0 \ (2), \\
      \frac{3n + 1}{4}  & \text{if} \ n \equiv 1 \ (4), \\
      \frac{3n - 1}{4}  & \text{if} \ n \equiv 3 \ (4).
    \end{cases}
    ]]>
  </Display>
  The reader may easily guess modulus, multiplier, divisor and prime set
  of this mapping himself -- it is however a good easy exercise for getting
  familiar with rcwa mappings to try to find its inverse by hand.
  The result can afterwards be checked using this package.
  It can be seen easily that the mapping <M>a</M> centralizes the involution
  <M>n \mapsto -n</M>. The permutation <M>a</M> has several finite cycles 
  (find out which!), and as far as I know it is an unsolved problem whether
  the cycle containing 8 is really infinite. Finally try to guess whether
  <M>a</M> is tame or wild! <P/>

  The next one is an example of an rcwa mapping of <M>\mathbb{Z}_{(2)}</M>:
  <Display>
    <![CDATA[
    f: \mathbb{Z}_{(2)} \ \longrightarrow \ \mathbb{Z}_{(2)}, \ \
    n \ \longmapsto \
    \begin{cases}
      \frac{1}{3}n - 7 & \text{if} \ n \equiv 0 \ (2), \\
      5n + \frac{1}{5} & \text{if} \ n \equiv 1 \ (2).
    \end{cases}
    ]]>
  </Display>
  The reader may test his understanding of the definitions by trying to
  determine the multiplier and the divisor of this mapping and by trying
  to figure out whether it is surjective, injective or even bijective --
  all of this should be quite easy. The mapping <M>f</M> is tame (why?).<P/>

  As our last example for now we give a wild element of
  RCWA(GF(2)[<M>x</M>]):
  <Display>
    <![CDATA[
    r \in {\rm RCWA}({\rm GF}(2)[x]), \ \
    P \ \longmapsto \
    \begin{cases}
      \frac{(x^2 + x + 1)P            }{x^2 + 1} &
        \text{if} \ P \equiv 0     \ (x^2 + 1), \\[1mm]
      \frac{(x^2 + x + 1)P +         x}{x^2 + 1} &
        \text{if} \ P \equiv 1     \ (x^2 + 1), \\[1mm]
      \frac{(x^2 + x + 1)P +       x^2}{x^2 + 1} &
        \text{if} \ P \equiv x     \ (x^2 + 1), \\[1mm]
      \frac{(x^2 + x + 1)P + (x^2 + x)}{x^2 + 1} &
        \text{if} \ P \equiv x + 1 \ (x^2 + 1).  \\
    \end{cases}
    ]]>
  </Display>
  The permutation <M>r</M> obviously fixes the degree of any polynomial,
  hence has only finite cycles. But there is an easy-to-check criterion
  which tells us that <M>r</M> is wild: its multiplier and divisor do not
  have the same prime divisors. Thus there cannot be an upper bound
  on the cycle lengths! <P/>

</Alt>

We proceed with a list briefly giving some results and remarks
(in arbitrary order).

<Index Key="Fürstenberg topology"></Index>

<List>

  <Mark>-</Mark>
  <Item>
    The group RCWA(<M>R</M>) acts highly transitive (i.e. <M>k</M>-fold
    transitive for any <M>k</M>) on <M>R</M>. It follows immediately that
    its centre is trivial, and from <Cite Key="DixonMortimer96"/>,
    Corollary 7.2A we know that any non-trivial normal subgroup must
    also act highly transitive on <M>R</M>.
  </Item>

  <Mark>-</Mark>
  <Item>
    A group can faithfully be represented as a tame rcwa group over the
    ring <M>R</M> if and only if it is isomorphic to a subgroup of the
    wreath product of the affine group of <M>R</M> with some large enough
    finite symmetric group.
  </Item>

  <Mark>-</Mark>
  <Item>
    The action of a tame group on the underlying ring <M>R</M> is
    imprimitive and there is a block system which consists of finitely many
    single residue classes, the so-called <E>respected class partition</E>.
    <M>\rightarrow</M>
    <Ref Attr ="RespectedClassPartition"
         Label="Respected class partition of rcwa group"/>.
  </Item>

  <Mark>-</Mark>
  <Item>
    Any tame rcwa group is conjugate to an integral group provided that
    the underlying ring <M>R</M> has residue class rings of any finite
    cardinality.
    <M>\rightarrow</M> <Ref Attr="IntegralConjugate"
                            Label="Integral conjugate of rcwa group"/>
    and <Ref Attr ="IntegralizingConjugator"
             Label="Integralizing conjugator of rcwa group"/>.
  </Item>

  <Mark>-</Mark>
  <Item>
    Even in wild groups we can often factor elements into generators --
    <Q>often</Q> in this context means something like <Q>if the element
    is a product of not more than 15 or 20 generators or inverses of
    generators</Q> -- of course this depends very much on the particular
    group and on the particular generators. Note that using the
    <Q>naive</Q> approach this would be far from being possible.
    <M>\rightarrow</M>
    <Ref Meth ="PreImagesRepresentative"
         Label="PreImagesRepresentative (element factorization)"/>.
  </Item>

  <Mark>-</Mark>
  <Item>
    The determinant induces an epimorphism from the group
    RCWA<M>^+(\Z)</M> of all class-wise order-preserving rcwa mappings
    of <M>\Z</M> onto <M>(\Z,+)</M>. An immediate consequence is that
    this large subgroup of RCWA(<M>\Z</M>) is not simple.    
    <M>\rightarrow</M> <Ref Meth="Determinant"/>
  </Item>

  <Mark>-</Mark>
  <Item>
    Taking the set of all residue classes of <M>R</M> as a basis of a
    topology turns RCWA(<M>R</M>) into a group of homoeomorphisms.
    Such a topology has already been introduced on the integers by Harry
    Fürstenberg in <Cite Key="Fuerstenberg55"/> for a topological proof
    of the infinitude of primes.
  </Item>

  <Mark>-</Mark>
  <Item>
    The group RCWA(<M>R</M>) acts transitive on the set of unions of
    finitely many residue classes distinct from the empty set and <M>R</M>
    itself, provided that <M>R</M> has a residue class ring of cardinality 2.
  </Item>

  <Mark>-</Mark>
  <Item>
    Assume that the ring <M>R</M> has a residue class ring of cardinality 2
    and that <M>S</M> is a non-empty union of finitely many residue classes
    of <M>R</M>. Then the group RCWA(<M>R</M>) has an isomorphic subgroup
    which acts faithfully on the set <M>S</M> and fixes its complement.
    Images under the corresponding <E>restriction monomorphisms</E> are
    algorithmically easy to compute.
    <M>\rightarrow</M> <Ref Oper ="Restriction"
                            Label="Restriction of an rcwa mapping"/>
    and <Ref Oper ="Restriction"
             Label="Restriction of an rcwa group"/>.
  </Item>

  <Mark>-</Mark>
  <Item>
    If <M>k</M> is coprime to the order of any torsion element of the
    group of units of <M>R</M>, the group RCWA(<M>R</M>) has only finitely
    many conjugacy classes of elements of order <M>k</M> --
    otherwise it has infinitely many such conjugacy classes.
    In the former case the number of such classes can be computed easily.
    <M>\rightarrow</M> <Ref Func="NrConjugacyClassesOfRCWAZOfOrder"/>.
  </Item>

  <Mark>-</Mark>
  <Item>
    <Q>Suitable</Q> rings admit wild rcwa mappings having only finite
    cycles. Of course in these cases the set of cycle lengths cannot be
    bounded to the above. The existence of such mappings can be observed
    relatively easy for rings like GF(<M>q</M>)[<M>x</M>] (see above), but
    e.g. on <M>\mathbb{Z}</M>, constructing examples is more difficult.
    <M>\rightarrow</M> Section&nbsp;<Ref Label="sec:WildButFiniteCycles"/>.
  </Item>

  <Mark>-</Mark>
  <Item>
    For better understanding given rcwa mappings as well as for constructing
    new ones with given properties, it is often helpful to associate directed
    graphs to them which reflect from which residue classes elements are
    mapped to which other residue classes -- we call these graphs
    <E>transition graphs</E>.
    <M>\rightarrow</M> <Ref Oper="TransitionGraph"/>.
  </Item>

  <Mark>-</Mark>
  <Item>
    There is no bijective rcwa mapping <M>g</M> such that the conjugate
    of the Collatz mapping under <M>g</M> maps all but finitely many
    positive integers to smaller ones. However, if the Collatz conjecture
    is true there must be some other permutation of the integers which
    serves this purpose.
  </Item>

</List>

We end this chapter by listing a few open problems (in arbitrary order).

<List>

  <Mark>-</Mark>
  <Item>
    Find out whether the groups RCWA(<M>R</M>) are simple or not.
    In case that they are not simple, determine a non-trivial normal
    subgroup and the structure of the factor group.
    Despite of the result concerning RCWA<M>^+(\Z)</M> I would consider
    this problem to be <Q>wide open</Q>, as the determinant mapping
    does not seem to have nice properties outside that large subgroup
    or for rings other than&nbsp;<M>\Z</M>.
    Do the groups RCWA(<M>R</M>) have non-trivial outer automorphisms?
  </Item>

  <Mark>-</Mark>
  <Item>
    What kind of structure can wild rcwa groups have? Only very little is
    currently known about this. E.g.: Does a free group of rank greater
    than 1 have a faithful rcwa representation? (almost certainly).
    Do the groups GL(<M>n</M>,<M>\mathbb{Z}</M>) have such a representation?
    (<Q>good question</Q>). Do all finitely presented groups have
    faithful rcwa representations? Are all finitely generated rcwa groups
    even finitely presented?
  </Item>

  <Mark>-</Mark>
  <Item>
    Is it possible that an rcwa group acts primitive but not highly
    transitive on one of its infinite orbits? There is some weak
    computational evidence suggesting a negative answer.
    <M>\rightarrow</M> <Ref Meth="RepresentativeAction"/> and
                       <Ref Oper="RepresentativeActionPreImage"/>.
    Are point stabilizers of finitely generated rcwa groups always
    finitely generated, also?
  </Item>

  <Mark>-</Mark>
  <Item>
    Prove the Collatz conjecture (maybe this is the hardest one).
    The theory of residue class-wise affine mappings gives rise to nice
    and natural generalizations of this long-standing conjecture.
    For related functionality of this package see
    <Ref Oper="ContractionCentre"/> and <Ref Attr="Divergence"/>.
    See also the examples given in
    Section&nbsp;<Ref Label="sec:SlowlyContractingMapping"/>,
    <Ref Label="sec:CollatzImagesAndPreImages"/> and
    <Ref Label="sec:CollatzMapping"/>.
  </Item>

</List>

<!-- #################################################################### -->

</Chapter>

<!-- #################################################################### -->
