<!-- #################################################################### -->
<!-- ##                                                                ## -->
<!-- ##  preface.xml         RCWA documentation           Stefan Kohl  ## -->
<!-- ##                                                                ## -->
<!-- ##  $Id$      ## -->
<!-- ##                                                                ## -->
<!-- #################################################################### -->

<Chapter Label="ch:preface"><Heading>Preface</Heading>

<!-- #################################################################### -->

<Section Label="sec:motivation">
<Heading>Motivation</Heading>

<Index Key="Collatz conjecture">Collatz conjecture</Index>
<Index Key="Collatz conjecture">Collatz mapping</Index>
The development of this package has originally been inspired by the famous
<M>3n+1</M>-Conjecture. This conjecture asserts that iterated application
of the Collatz mapping
<Alt Only="LaTeX">
  <Display>
  <![CDATA[
    T: \ \Z \longrightarrow \Z, \ \ \ \
    n \ \longmapsto \
    \begin{cases}
      \frac{n}{2}    & \text{if} \ n \ \text{even}, \\
      \frac{3n+1}{2} & \text{if} \ n \ \text{odd}
    \end{cases}
  ]]>
  </Display>
</Alt>
<Alt Only="Text,HTML"><Verb><![CDATA[
                                       /
                                      | n/2 if n even,
               T:  Z -> Z,   n  |->  <
                                      | (3n+1)/2 if n odd
                                       \
]]></Verb></Alt>
to any given positive integer eventually yields&nbsp;1. <P/>

The <M>3n+1</M>-Conjecture has been made by Lothar Collatz in the 1930s,
and is still lacking a proof today.
Jeffrey C. Lagarias has written and maintains a comprehensive annotated
bibliography <Cite Key="Lagarias06"/>, which currently lists about
200&nbsp;references to publications related to Collatz' conjecture.
None of the articles mentioned there tries to attack the problem by means
of group theory or investigates the structure of groups generated by
bijective mappings which are <Q>similar to the Collatz mapping</Q>,
i.e. <E>residue class-wise affine</E>.
In fact, <E>residue class-wise affine groups</E> apparently
have not been treated anywhere in the literature before. <P/>

After having investigated these objects for a couple of years,
the author feels that this is a gap which is worth to be filled.

</Section>

<!-- #################################################################### -->

<Section Label="sec:GroupsWhichEmbed">
<Heading>Groups which can be represented</Heading>

This section lists some types of groups which are known to be representable
as residue class-wise affine groups. Proofs of most of the results have not
yet appeared in print, but can be found in the preprint <E>A Simple Group
Generated by Involutions Interchanging Residue Classes of the Integers</E>
on the author's homepage. <P/>

Obviously, the infinite dihedral group <M>\langle n \mapsto -n,
n \mapsto n+1 \rangle</M> can be represented. Further the class of
representable groups is closed under forming direct products and under
forming wreath products with finite groups and with the infinite cyclic
group <M>(\Z,+)</M>.
Free groups and free products of finite groups can be represented as well.
Further there are divisible torsion groups and finitely generated groups
with unsolvable membership problem which have faithful residue class-wise
affine representations. In principle this package permits to construct
and investigate groups of all mentioned types. <P/>

The group which is generated by all <E>class transpositions</E>
-- these are involutions which interchange two disjoint residue classes,
see <Ref Func="ClassTransposition" Label="r1, m1, r2, m2"/> -- is a simple
group which contains all the above groups. It has uncountably many simple
subgroups.

</Section>

<!-- #################################################################### -->

<Section Label="sec:Purpose">
<Heading>Purpose of this package</Heading>

So far, compared to classes of groups like for example matrix groups,
finite permutation groups or polycyclic groups, only relatively basic facts
about residue class-wise affine groups are known. This package is intended
to serve as a tool for obtaining a better understanding of their rich and
interesting group theoretical and combinatorial structure.

</Section>

<!-- #################################################################### -->

<Section Label="sec:Scope">
<Heading>Scope of this package</Heading>

This package being a research tool which can be applied in various ways to
various different problems, it is simply not possible to say what can be
found out with its help about which mappings or groups.
The best way to get an idea about this is likely to experiment with the
examples discussed in this manual and included in the file
<File>pkg/rcwa/examples/examples.g</File>. <P/>

Of course this package often does not provide an out-of-the-box solution for
a given problem. At the beginning the user may perhaps notice long
runtimes for seemingly easy things. But with some experience he will learn
to estimate how long something will take and to see why raising some
harmlessly-looking mapping to the 20th power would take terabytes of
memory, while one can easily find out nontrivial things about groups which
look much more complicate. Quite often it is possible to find an answer for
a given question by using an interactive trial-and-error approach. <P/>

Among many other results, with substancial help of this package the author
has found a proof that the group generated by all class transpositions
is simple. Interactive sessions with this package have also lead to the
development of a method for factoring residue class-wise affine permutations
into involutions which have a particularly simple structure
(see&nbsp;<Ref Attr="FactorizationIntoCSCRCT" Label="g"/>).

</Section>

<!-- #################################################################### -->

</Chapter>

<!-- #################################################################### -->
