<!-- #################################################################### -->
<!-- ##                                                                ## -->
<!-- ##  preface.xml         RCWA documentation           Stefan Kohl  ## -->
<!-- ##                                                                ## -->
<!-- ##  $Id$      ## -->
<!-- ##                                                                ## -->
<!-- #################################################################### -->

<Chapter Label="ch:preface"><Heading>Preface</Heading>

<!-- #################################################################### -->

<Section Label="sec:motivation">
<Heading>Motivation</Heading>

<Index Key="Collatz conjecture">Collatz conjecture</Index>
<Index Key="Collatz conjecture">Collatz mapping</Index>
The development of this package has originally been motivated by the famous
<M>3n+1</M> - Conjecture, which asserts that iterated application of the
Collatz mapping
<Alt Only="LaTeX">
  <Display>
  <![CDATA[
    T: \ \mathbb{Z} \longrightarrow \mathbb{Z}, \ \ \ \
    n \ \longmapsto \
    \begin{cases}
      \frac{n}{2}    & \text{if} \ n \ \text{even}, \\
      \frac{3n+1}{2} & \text{if} \ n \ \text{odd}
    \end{cases}
  ]]>
  </Display>
</Alt>
<Alt Only="Text,HTML"><Verb><![CDATA[
                                       /
                                      | n/2 if n even,
               T:  Z -> Z,   n  |->  <
                                      | (3n+1)/2 if n odd
                                       \
]]></Verb></Alt>
to any given positive integer eventually yields&nbsp;1. <P/>

This has been conjectured by Lothar Collatz in the 1930s, and is still
an unsolved problem today.
Jeffrey C. Lagarias has written and maintains a commented bibliography
<Cite Key="Lagarias06"/>, which currently lists about 200&nbsp;references
to publications related to Collatz' conjecture.
None of the articles mentioned there tries to attack the problem by means
of group theory, or investigates the structure of groups generated by
bijective mappings which are <Q>similar to the Collatz mapping</Q>,
i.e. <E>residue class-wise affine</E>.
In fact, <E>residue class-wise affine groups</E> apparently
have not been treated anywhere in the literature before. <P/>

After having investigated these objects for a couple of years,
the author feels that this is a gap which is worth to be filled.

</Section>

<!-- #################################################################### -->

<Section Label="sec:purpose">
<Heading>Purpose of this package</Heading>

So far, compared to classes of groups like for example matrix groups,
finite permutation groups or polycyclic groups, only relatively basic facts
about residue class-wise affine groups are known. This package is intended
to serve as a tool for obtaining a better understanding of their rich and
interesting group theoretical and combinatorial structure. <P/>

This manual is pure software documentation, and as such it does not contain
any theorems or proofs. In a few places, where this is absolutely necessary
for understanding what some function is good for, corresponding mathematical
assertions are made. Proofs of all of them as well as a detailed
introduction into the subject can be found in the author's
PhD thesis&nbsp;<Cite Key="Kohl05"/>.
A copy of this thesis and an english translation thereof are distributed
with this package (see <F>thesis/thesis.pdf</F> resp.
<F>thesis/thesis&uscore;e.pdf</F>).

</Section>

<Alt Only="LaTeX">\pagebreak[4]</Alt>

<!-- #################################################################### -->

<Section Label="sec:noteaboutcontents">
<Heading>Scope of this package</Heading>

This package being a research tool which can be applied in various ways to
various different problems, it is simply not possible to say what can be
found out with it about which mappings or groups. The best way to get an idea
about this is likely to experiment with the examples discussed in this
manual and included in the file <File>pkg/rcwa/examples/examples.g</File>.
Another source of examples is the <Ref Meth="Random"
Label="RCWA( Integers )"/> - function. If you have &LaTeX; and
<Package>xdvi</Package> installed, you can nicely display examples of
residue class-wise affine mappings by repeatedly issueing
<C>Display(Random(RCWA(Integers)):xdvi);</C>. <P/>

Often the package does not provide an out-of-the-box solution for a given
problem. At the beginning you will perhaps notice extremely long runtimes
for seemingly trivial things. But with some experience you will learn to
estimate in advance how long something will take and to see why raising some
harmlessly-looking mapping to the 20th power would take terabytes of memory,
while one can easily find out nontrivial things about some group which
looks much more complicate. Quite often it is possible to find an answer for
a given question by using an interactive trial-and-error approach. <P/>

Among many other results, with substancial help of this package the author
has found a non-trivial normal subgroup of the group of all residue
class-wise affine permutations of the integers. Interactive sessions with
this package have also lead to the development of a method for factoring
residue class-wise affine permutations into involutions which have a
particularly simple structure (see <Ref Attr="FactorizationIntoGenerators"
Label="g"/>).

</Section>

<!-- #################################################################### -->

<Section Label="sec:acknowledgements">
<Heading>Acknowledgements</Heading>

I would like to thank Bettina&nbsp;Eick for her kind help in
trying to make this package and in particular its documentation more
useful and more interesting for a larger number of people.
Furthermore I would like to thank the two anonymous referees for their
constructive criticism and helpful suggestions. <P/>

If you use &RCWA; in some work leading to a publication, I ask you to cite
it just as you would cite a journal article. I would be grateful for any
bug reports, comments or suggestions and of course for reports of results
found with the help of this package.

<Alt Only="Text"> </Alt>
<Alt Only="HTML">
<![CDATA[
  <P align = right> Stefan Kohl </P>
]]>
</Alt>
<Alt Only="LaTeX">
<![CDATA[
  \vfill \noindent Stuttgart, \today \hfill Stefan Kohl
]]>
</Alt>

</Section>

<!-- #################################################################### -->

</Chapter>

<!-- #################################################################### -->
