<!-- #################################################################### -->
<!-- ##                                                                ## -->
<!-- ##  preface.xml         RCWA documentation           Stefan Kohl  ## -->
<!-- ##                                                                ## -->
<!-- ##  $Id$       ## -->
<!-- ##                                                                ## -->
<!-- #################################################################### -->

<Chapter Label="ch:preface"><Heading>Preface</Heading>

<!-- #################################################################### -->

This package deals with a certain kind of mappings of euclidean rings onto
themselves, namely those which are affine on any residue class modulo
<M>m</M>, where <M>m</M> is some modulus depending on the particular mapping.
It provides functionality for doing computations with such mappings over
the ring of integers, its semilocalizations and over polynomial rings in
one variable over a finite field.
In the introduction I will give brief definitions of the basic terms. <P/>

<Index Key="dynamical systems">dynamical systems</Index>
<Index Key="Markov chains">Markov chains</Index>
It seems that so far nobody has studied the mentioned mappings from an
algebraic point of view, although there have been some publications which
shed light on the topic by investigating related dynamical systems and
Markov chains. In this context I would like to mention a monograph by
Günther J. Wirsching <Cite Key="Wirsching98"/> and an article by
G. Venturini <Cite Key="Venturini92"/>.
Permutation group-theoretic work which might be considered to be weakly
related to this topic has been done by Hans Läuchli and  Peter M. Neumann
<Cite Key="LaeuchliNeumann88"/>, but this does not deal with any kind
of permutation groups over rings or of countable permutation groups,
and doesn't seem to help anything in the given context.
<Index Key="permutation groups">permutation groups</Index>
<Index Key="permutation groups" Subkey="over rings"></Index> 
<Index Key="permutation groups" Subkey="countable"></Index>
For a general survey of results concerning infinite permutation groups
see <Cite Key="BhattacharjeeMacphersonMoellerNeumann98"/>.

<Index Key="Collatz conjecture">Collatz conjecture</Index>
<Index Key="Collatz conjecture">Collatz mapping</Index>
Introducing the given kind of mappings, permutations and representations
of groups was originally motivated by my investigations concerning the
Collatz- (<M>3n+1</M>-) conjecture (which claims that iterated application
of the <E>Collatz mapping</E> <M>T</M> which maps even <M>n</M> to <M>n/2</M>
and odd <M>n</M> to <M>(3n+1)/2</M> eventually would take any positive
integer to 1; for an annotated bibliography listing about 100 publications
on this problem see <Cite Key="Lagarias98"/>), but now, residue class-wise
affine representations of groups seem to be an interesting topic of its own.
<P/>

I developed this package as a crucial tool for investigating a large number
of examples and getting deep enough insight into the structure of residue
class-wise affine mappings and groups to be able to start building a theory
of them from the bottom in my thesis <Cite Key="Kohl04"/>. <P/>

I would be grateful for any bug reports, comments or suggestions.

<Alt Only="Text"> </Alt>
<Alt Only="HTML">
  <![CDATA[
    <P align = right> Stefan Kohl </P>
  ]]>
</Alt>
<Alt Only="LaTeX">
  <![CDATA[
    \vfill \hfill Stefan Kohl
  ]]>
</Alt>

<!-- #################################################################### -->

</Chapter>

<!-- #################################################################### -->


