<!-- #################################################################### -->
<!-- ##                                                                ## -->
<!-- ##  preface.xml         RCWA documentation           Stefan Kohl  ## -->
<!-- ##                                                                ## -->
<!-- ##  $Id$      ## -->
<!-- ##                                                                ## -->
<!-- #################################################################### -->

<Chapter Label="ch:preface"><Heading>Preface</Heading>

<!-- #################################################################### -->

<Section Label="sec:motivation">
<Heading>Motivation</Heading>

<Index Key="Collatz conjecture">Collatz conjecture</Index>
<Index Key="Collatz conjecture">Collatz mapping</Index>
The development of this package has originally been inspired by the famous
<M>3n+1</M>-Conjecture. This conjecture asserts that iterated application
of the Collatz mapping
<Alt Only="LaTeX">
  <Display>
  <![CDATA[
    T: \ \Z \longrightarrow \Z, \ \ \ \
    n \ \longmapsto \
    \begin{cases}
      \frac{n}{2}    & \text{if} \ n \ \text{even}, \\
      \frac{3n+1}{2} & \text{if} \ n \ \text{odd}
    \end{cases}
  ]]>
  </Display>
</Alt>
<Alt Only="Text,HTML"><Verb><![CDATA[
                                       /
                                      | n/2 if n even,
               T:  Z -> Z,   n  |->  <
                                      | (3n+1)/2 if n odd
                                       \
]]></Verb></Alt>
to any given positive integer eventually yields&nbsp;1. <P/>

The <M>3n+1</M>-Conjecture has been made by Lothar Collatz in the 1930s,
and is still lacking a proof today.
Jeffrey C. Lagarias has written and maintains a comprehensive annotated
bibliography <Cite Key="Lagarias06"/>, which currently lists about
200&nbsp;references to publications related to Collatz' conjecture.
None of the articles mentioned there tries to attack the problem by means
of group theory or investigates the structure of groups generated by
bijective mappings which are <Q>similar to the Collatz mapping</Q>,
i.e. <E>residue class-wise affine</E>.
In fact, <E>residue class-wise affine groups</E> apparently
have not been treated anywhere in the literature before. <P/>

After having investigated these objects for a couple of years,
the author feels that this is a gap which is worth to be filled.

</Section>

<!-- #################################################################### -->

<Section Label="sec:GroupsWhichEmbed">
<Heading>Groups which can be represented</Heading>

This section lists some types of groups which are known to be representable
as residue class-wise affine groups. Proofs of most of the results have not
yet appeared in print, but can be found in preprints on the author's
homepage. <P/>

Obviously, the infinite dihedral group <M>\langle n \mapsto -n,
n \mapsto n+1 \rangle</M> can be represented. Further the class of
representable groups is closed under forming wreath products with finite
groups (cp.&nbsp;<Cite Key="Kohl05"/>, Corollary&nbsp;2.3.3 and
Theorem&nbsp;2.6.1) and with the infinite cyclic group <M>(\Z,+)</M>.
Free groups and free products of finite groups can be represented as well.
Further there are divisible torsion groups and finitely generated groups
with unsolvable membership problem which have faithful residue class-wise
affine representations. In principle this package permits to construct
and investigate groups of all mentioned types. <P/>

The group which is generated by all <E>class transpositions</E>
-- these are involutions which interchange two disjoint residue classes,
see <Ref Func="ClassTransposition" Label="r1, m1, r2, m2"/> -- is a simple
group which contains all the above groups. It has uncountably many simple
subgroups.

</Section>

<!-- #################################################################### -->

<Section Label="sec:Purpose">
<Heading>Purpose of this package</Heading>

So far, compared to classes of groups like for example matrix groups,
finite permutation groups or polycyclic groups, only relatively basic facts
about residue class-wise affine groups are known. This package is intended
to serve as a tool for obtaining a better understanding of their rich and
interesting group theoretical and combinatorial structure. <P/>

This manual is pure software documentation, and as such it does not contain
any theorems or proofs. Mathematical assertions are usually only made in
places where they are necessary for understanding the functionality of this
package. Proofs of many of them as well as a detailed introduction into the
subject can be found in the author's PhD thesis&nbsp;<Cite Key="Kohl05"/>.
A copy of this thesis and an english translation thereof are distributed
with this package (see <F>thesis/thesis.pdf</F> resp.
<F>thesis/thesis&uscore;e.pdf</F>).

</Section>

<!-- #################################################################### -->

<Section Label="sec:Scope">
<Heading>Scope of this package</Heading>

This package being a research tool which can be applied in various ways to
various different problems, it is simply not possible to say what can be
found out with it about which mappings or groups. The best way to get an
idea about this is likely to experiment with the examples discussed in this
manual and included in the file <File>pkg/rcwa/examples/examples.g</File>.
Another source of examples is the <C>Random</C> - function. If you have
&LaTeX; and <Package>xdvi</Package> installed, you can nicely display
examples of residue class-wise affine mappings by repeatedly issueing
<C>Display(Random(RCWA(Integers)):xdvi);</C>. <P/>

Of course this package often does not provide an out-of-the-box solution for
a given problem. At the beginning you may perhaps notice extremely long
runtimes for seemingly easy things. But with some experience you will learn
to estimate how long something will take and to see why raising some
harmlessly-looking mapping to the 20th power would take terabytes of
memory, while one can easily find out nontrivial things about groups which
look much more complicate. Quite often it is possible to find an answer for
a given question by using an interactive trial-and-error approach. <P/>

Among many other results, with substancial help of this package the author
has found a proof that the group generated by all class transpositions
is simple. Interactive sessions with this package have also lead to the
development of a method for factoring residue class-wise affine permutations
into involutions which have a particularly simple structure
(see&nbsp;<Ref Attr="FactorizationIntoCSCRCT" Label="g"/>).

</Section>

<!-- #################################################################### -->

<Section Label="sec:Acknowledgements">
<Heading>Acknowledgements</Heading>

I would like to thank Bettina&nbsp;Eick for her kind help in
trying to make this package and in particular its documentation more
useful and more interesting for a larger number of people.
Further I would like to thank the two anonymous referees for their
constructive criticism and helpful suggestions. 
I am grateful to Laurent Bartholdi for his interesting hint on how
to construct wreath products of residue class-wise affine groups with
<M>(\Z,+)</M>. <P/>

If you use &RCWA; in some work leading to a publication, I ask you to cite
it just as you would cite a journal article. I would be grateful for any
bug reports, comments or suggestions and of course for reports of results
found with the help of this package.

<Alt Only="Text"> </Alt>
<Alt Only="HTML">
<![CDATA[
  <p align = "right"> Stefan Kohl </p>
]]>
</Alt>
<Alt Only="LaTeX">
<![CDATA[
  \vfill \noindent Stuttgart, \today \hfill Stefan Kohl
]]>
</Alt>

</Section>

<!-- #################################################################### -->

</Chapter>

<!-- #################################################################### -->
