<!-- #################################################################### -->
<!-- ##                                                                ## -->
<!-- ##  preface.xml         RCWA documentation           Stefan Kohl  ## -->
<!-- ##                                                                ## -->
<!-- ##  $Id$      ## -->
<!-- ##                                                                ## -->
<!-- #################################################################### -->

<Chapter Label="ch:preface"><Heading>Preface</Heading>

<!-- #################################################################### -->

<Index Key="Collatz conjecture">Collatz conjecture</Index>
<Index Key="Collatz conjecture">Collatz mapping</Index>
In the 1930s Lothar Collatz proposed the following procedure:

<List>

  <Mark>1.</Mark>
  <Item>
    Choose a positive integer <M>n</M>.
  </Item>

  <Mark>2.</Mark>
  <Item>
    Divide <M>n</M> by 2 if it is even, and multiply it by 3 and add 1
    otherwise.
  </Item>

  <Mark>3.</Mark>
  <Item>
    Terminate if <M>n = 1</M> and continue with step 2 otherwise.
  </Item>

</List>

He conjectured that this process eventually terminates regardless of the
choice of the starting value <M>n</M>.

To give an easy example: starting at 15, we get the sequence 15, 46, 23, 70,
35, 106, 53, 160, 80, 40, 20, 10, 5, 16, 8, 4, 2, 1.

In fact, Collatz' problem is still unsolved today, despite the fact that
there have been more than 100 publications treating aspects of it so far --
for an annotated bibliography listing many of them see
<Cite Key="Lagarias98"/>.

We look at the mapping introduced in step 2 above and ask for
generalizations. There are several obvious things we can do:

<List>

  <Mark>1.</Mark>
  <Item>
    We can replace the mappings <M>n \mapsto n/2</M> and
    <M>n \mapsto 3n+1</M> by <Q>suitable</Q> other
    mappings.
  </Item>

  <Mark>2.</Mark>
  <Item>
    Instead of making the choice of the mapping depend
    on whether <M>n</M> is even or odd, we can introduce
    more alternatives and make it depend on <M>n</M> mod
    <M>m</M> for some modulus <M>m</M> greater than 2.
  </Item>

  <Mark>3.</Mark>
  <Item>
    The Collatz mapping is defined over the ring of integers --
    there may be other rings which admit similar mappings.
  </Item>

</List>

This is the motivation for the following definitions: <P/>

<Index Key="rcwa mapping" Subkey="definition"></Index> 
Let <M>R</M> be an infinite euclidean domain which is not a field and all
of whose proper residue class rings are finite.
We call a mapping <M>f</M> from <M>R</M> into itself <E>residue class-wise
affine</E>, or in short an <E>rcwa</E> mapping, if there is a non-zero
modulus <M>m \in R</M> such that for any residue class <M>r(m) \in R/mR</M>
there are coefficients <M>a_{r(m)}, b_{r(m)}, c_{r(m)} \in R</M> such that
the restriction of <M>f</M> to <M>r(m)</M> (in this context we regard
residue classes as sets) is given by <P/>
<Alt Only="Text"> 
  <![CDATA[

                      n  -->  ( a_r(m) * n + b_r(m) ) / c_r(m).

  ]]>
</Alt>
<Alt Only="HTML">
  <![CDATA[
    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;
    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;
    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;
    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;
    n  -->  ( a_r(m) * n + b_r(m) ) / c_r(m).
  ]]>
</Alt>
<Alt Only="LaTeX">
  <Display>
    n \ \mapsto \ \frac{a_{r(m)} \cdot n + b_{r(m)}}{c_{r(m)}}.
  </Display>
</Alt>
We always assume that all fractions are reduced, i.e. that
<M>\gcd( a_{r(m)}, b_{r(m)}, c_{r(m)} ) = 1</M>, and that no proper divisor
of <M>m</M> shares the given property. Apart from the restrictions imposed by
the condition that the image of any residue class <M>r(m)</M> under <M>f</M>
must be a subset of <M>R</M> and that we cannot divide by 0, the coefficients
<M>a_{r(m)}</M>, <M>b_{r(m)}</M> and <M>c_{r(m)}</M> can be any ring elements.
<Index Key="rcwa mapping" Subkey="modulus"></Index>
We call <M>m</M> the <E>modulus</E> of <M>f</M>.
When talking about the <E>product</E> of some rcwa mappings we always mean
their composition as mappings, and by the inverse of a bijective rcwa mapping
we mean its inverse mapping. <P/>

The set RCWA(<M>R</M>) <M>\ := \ </M> { <M>\{ \ g \in</M> Sym(<M>R</M>)
<M>\ | \ g</M> is residue class-wise affine <M>\}</M> } is closed under
multiplication and taking inverses (this can be verified easily), hence
forms a subgroup of Sym(<M>R</M>). For reasons of cardinality this
subgroup is proper.
<Index Key="rcwa group" Subkey="definition"></Index>
We call a subgroup of RCWA(<M>R</M>) a <E>residue class-wise affine</E>
group, or in short an <E>rcwa</E> group.
<Index Key="rcwa group" Subkey="modulus"></Index>
We define the <E>modulus</E> of an rcwa group by the lcm of the moduli of
its elements in case such an lcm exists, and by 0 otherwise. <P/>

This package provides functionality for computing with rcwa mappings of
the ring of integers, its semilocalizations and of polynomial rings in one
variable over a finite field, as well as with rcwa groups over these rings.
The reasons for choosing the given rings are basically the following:
The Collatz conjecture is a question about the integers, thus we clearly
want to look at these. The ring <M>\mathbb{Z}</M> has characteristic 0 and
infinitely many prime elements. A natural question which arises is what
happens when moving to some ring with characteristic <M>p</M> or with only
finitely many prime elements.
The rings GF(<M>q</M>)[<M>x</M>] and <M>\mathbb{Z}_{(\pi)}</M> are probably
the examples which permit the most efficient computational treatment. <P/>

There are relatively elaborate methods for dealing with rcwa groups which
have a comparatively easy structure, namely those having non-zero modulus.
We call such groups and the mappings generating cyclic such groups
<E>tame</E>.
There are theorems stating that tame groups act imprimitively on the
underlying ring <M>R</M>, that there are block systems consisting of only
finitely many single residue classes, that a tame group is always
isomorphic to a subgroup of the wreath product of the affine group with
some large enough finite symmetric group and that any of the latter
groups can faithfully be represented as a tame rcwa group.
The groups which are not tame are much more difficult to examine and
can act highly transitive on the ring <M>R</M> or on subsets of it.
Many important questions for such groups might be conjectured to be
algorithmically undecidable -- such conjectures are for example supported
by the difficulty of the Collatz problem as well as by the fact that there
are concretely given cycles of concretely given bijective rcwa mappings
which are conjectured but not known to be infinite(!) -- see the
introduction. The structure of these groups also looks much more
<Q>mysterious</Q>. Thus we call these groups and the mappings generating
cyclic such groups <E>wild</E> -- but nethertheless there is e.g. an
algorithm for factoring elements into generators, which usually works
reasonably well if the resulting word would not be <Q>too long</Q>.
In any case please note that also tame mappings can generate wild groups --
given two or more arbitrary tame mappings it is quite likely that the
group generated by them is wild. <P/>

<Index Key="dynamical systems">dynamical systems</Index>
<Index Key="Markov chains">Markov chains</Index>
It seems that so far nobody has studied rcwa mappings from an
algebraic point of view, although there have been some publications which
shed light on the topic by investigating related dynamical systems and
Markov chains. In this context I would like to mention a monograph by
Günther J. Wirsching <Cite Key="Wirsching98"/> and an article by
G. Venturini <Cite Key="Venturini92"/>.
Permutation group-theoretic work which might be considered to be weakly
related to this topic has been done by Hans Läuchli and  Peter M. Neumann
<Cite Key="LaeuchliNeumann88"/>.
<Index Key="permutation groups">permutation groups</Index>
<Index Key="permutation groups" Subkey="over rings"></Index> 
<Index Key="permutation groups" Subkey="countable"></Index>
For a general survey of results concerning infinite permutation groups
see <Cite Key="BhattacharjeeMacphersonMoellerNeumann98"/>. <P/>

The main reason for me to develop this package was the desire to get a
suitable tool for investigating a large number of examples and getting deep
enough insight into the structure of residue class-wise affine mappings and
groups to be able to start building a theory of them from the bottom in my
thesis <Cite Key="Kohl04"/>. <P/>

At this point I would like to thank Bettina Eick for her kind help in
trying to make this package and in particular its documentation more
useful and more interesting for a larger number of people. <P/>

I would be grateful for any bug reports, comments or suggestions.

<Alt Only="Text"> </Alt>
<Alt Only="HTML">
<![CDATA[
  <P align = right> Stefan Kohl </P>
]]>
</Alt>
<Alt Only="LaTeX">
<![CDATA[
  \vfill \hfill Stefan Kohl
]]>
</Alt>

<!-- #################################################################### -->

</Chapter>

<!-- #################################################################### -->

